

ABOUT ME

I am a biomechanist interested in the impact of lateral bicycle sway and rider center of mass motion on cycling performance. I have a passion for optimizing athletic performance, having worked as a strength and conditioning coach and performance analyst. I'm also an avid cyclist with a healthy addiction to espresso coffee.

KNOWLEDGE/SKILLS

- 3D MOTION ANALYSIS
- INVERSE DYNAMICS
- MUSCULO-SKELETAL MODELLING
- MATLAB PROGRAMMING
- ELECTROMYOGRAPHY
- GPS ANALYSIS
- ATHLETIC PERFORMANCE
- SPORTS NUTRITION

ROSS WILKINSON

PH.D. CANDIDATE (BIOMECHANICS) & SPORTS SCIENTIST

Brisbane, QLD, Australia (+61) 431-527-473 r.wilkinson@uq.edu.au

EDUCATION

THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND

Brisbane, QLD, AUS 2016 – Present

Ph.D. Candidate

- Thesis title: Effect of Lateral Bicycle Sway and Riding Posture on Mechanical Effectiveness and Efficiency in Cycling
- Advisors: Professor Andrew Cresswell and Associate Professor Glen Lichtwark

THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND

Brisbane, QLD, AUS 2008 – 2012

Bachelor of Exercise and Sports Sciences – Honors 1A

- Awarded Dean's Commendation for High Achievement
- Honors project: The Correlation Between the 30-15 Intermittent Fitness Test and a Novel Test of Running Performance
- Advisors: Vince Kelly, Ph.D and Anthony Wood

TEACHING & SUPERVISION

THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND

Brisbane, QLD, AUS 2016 – Present

THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND

Brisbane, QLD, AUS 2016 – Present

Tutor

- Biomechanics (BIOL2630)
- Motor Control & Learning (NEUR2530)
- Neuromechanical Basis of Human Movement (NEUR3733)

Honors Advisor

- Project: The validity of wearable inertial measurement units for tracking center of mass position during non-seated cycling
- Project: Center of mass movement during non-seated cycling
- Project: Joint power contributions during non-seated cycling
- Project: Lower limb muscle activity during non-seated cycling

PREVIOUS EMPLOYMENT

99 BIKES PTY LTD

Brisbane, QLD, AUS 2013 – 2016

Store Manager & Sales Consultant

- Managed my store to a company record annual profit during my first year of employment
- Set company record for highest sales by a consultant in my first month of employment

BRISBANE LIONS AUSTRALIAN FOOTBALL CLUB

Brisbane, QLD, AUS 2012 – 2013

Performance Analyst

- Assisted the athletic performance and rehabilitation team during the 2012 AFL Season.
- Main responsibilities included GPS data analysis, program design and athlete supervision.

THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND SPORTS ACADEMY

Brisbane, QLD, AUS 2011 – 2012

Strength and Conditioning Coach

 Designed and implemented physical performance programs for a number of teams and individuals in a variety of sports including Rugby, AFL, Netball and Rowing.